<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Resources For Jazz Guitar</title>
  <subtitle>Practice materials and serious music theory for Jazz Guitar.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/" />
  <updated>2024-10-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Chester Jankowski</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Generated Collections</title>
    <link href="https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/generated-collections/" />
    <updated>2024-10-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/generated-collections/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Generating the collections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, we will borrow some concepts from abstract algebra and group theory to explore some aspects of the scales and chords we commonly use in jazz. Please do not be put off by the prospect of math, it will be kept at a very simple level. Looking at the collections in this way illuminates how they are constructed, how they are symmetrical, and it is especially helpful in understanding subset relations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definition: a generated collection is formed by repeatedly adding a single interval, which we term the &amp;quot;generator.&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s begin with a really simple example, and use the generator of 1 semitone. We will start with a single pitch class {0}. In the first iteration, we add an interval of 1, which gives us the set {0,1}. In the second iteration, we add another interval of 1, and now have the set {0,1,2}. If we continue iterating, after eleven steps, we will have the set {0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11}, which we can think of as the chromatic scale, or in pc set theory what is often termed the &amp;quot;aggregate&amp;quot;. Since we are doing math in mod 12, we can keep iterating, but we won&#39;t add any new pitch classes, the set will just keep cycling through the same integers; this is sometimes termed a &amp;quot;cyclic set&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&#39;s try using a generator of 2 semitones. After five iterations, we will have the set {0,2,4,6,8,10}, which is the wholetone scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A generator of 3 semitones gives us the set {0,3,6,9}, which is a diminished 7th chord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A generator of 4 semitones gives us the set {0,4,8}, which is an augmented triad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The generator of 5 semitones is another special case, so let&#39;s look at all the iterations of this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{0}&lt;br&gt;
{0,5}&lt;br&gt;
{0,5,10}&lt;br&gt;
{0,5,10,3}&lt;br&gt;
{0,5,10,3,8}&lt;br&gt;
{0,5,10,3,8,1}&lt;br&gt;
{0,5,10,3,8,1,6}&lt;br&gt;
{0,5,10,3,8,1,6,11}&lt;br&gt;
{0,5,10,3,8,1,6,11,4}&lt;br&gt;
{0,5,10,3,8,1,6,11,4,9}&lt;br&gt;
{0,5,10,3,8,1,6,11,4,9,2}&lt;br&gt;
{0,5,10,3,8,1,6,11,4,9,2,7}&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the same sets with the pitch classes arranged in ascending integer order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{0}&lt;br&gt;
{0,5}&lt;br&gt;
{0,5,10}&lt;br&gt;
{0,3,5,10}&lt;br&gt;
{0,3,5,8,10}&lt;br&gt;
{0,1,3,5,8,10}&lt;br&gt;
{0,1,3,5,6,8,10}&lt;br&gt;
{0,1,3,5,6,8,10,11}&lt;br&gt;
{0,1,3,4,5,6,8,10,11}&lt;br&gt;
{0,1,3,4,5,6,8,9,10,11}&lt;br&gt;
{0,1,2,3,4,5,6,8,9,10,11}&lt;br&gt;
{0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11}&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at these sets closely, we see that they are some of the most important sets used in jazz. The set with cardinality 5, {0,3,5,8,10}, is the pentatonic scale. The set with cardinality 6, {0,1,3,5,8,10}, is the hexatonic scale. The set with cardinality 7, {0,1,3,5,6,8,10}, is the diatonic collection. It is also worth noting that this set is the first iteration which contains the interval of a tritone. The set with cardinality 9, {0,1,3,4,5,6,8,10,11}, is the bebop scale. And finally, the set with cardinality 12, {0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11}, is the chromatic scale, or aggregate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&#39;s go on the next generator, an interval of 6 semitones. {0,6}. Well, that does seem a bit anticlimactic, after the fecundity of generator 5, does it not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the generator of 7 semitones, I will once again list all iterations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{0}&lt;br&gt;
{0,7}&lt;br&gt;
{0,7,2}&lt;br&gt;
{0,7,2,9}&lt;br&gt;
{0,7,2,9,4}&lt;br&gt;
{0,7,2,9,4,11}&lt;br&gt;
{0,7,2,9,4,11,6}&lt;br&gt;
{0,7,2,9,4,11,6,1}&lt;br&gt;
{0,7,2,9,4,11,6,1,8}&lt;br&gt;
{0,7,2,9,4,11,6,1,8,3}&lt;br&gt;
{0,7,2,9,4,11,6,1,8,3,10}&lt;br&gt;
{0,7,2,9,4,11,6,1,8,3,10,5}&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And once again, in ascending pitch class integer order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{0}&lt;br&gt;
{0,7}&lt;br&gt;
{0,2,7}&lt;br&gt;
{0,2,7,9}&lt;br&gt;
{0,2,4,7,9}&lt;br&gt;
{0,2,4,7,9,11}&lt;br&gt;
{0,2,4,6,7,9,11}&lt;br&gt;
{0,1,2,4,6,7,9,11}&lt;br&gt;
{0,1,2,4,6,7,8,9,11}&lt;br&gt;
{0,1,2,3,4,6,7,8,9,11}&lt;br&gt;
{0,1,2,3,4,6,7,8,9,10,11}&lt;br&gt;
{0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11}&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s compare the cardinality 7 sets from the 5 and 7 semitone generators:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{0,5,10,3,8,1,6}&lt;br&gt;
{0,7,2,9,4,11,6}&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see that the two sets are inversionally related. So, for example, instead of using a generator of 7 semitones for the second set, we could use a generator of -5 semitones and get the same result. Starting with {0}, we add an interval of -5, which gives us, mod 12, {0,7}. Adding another interval of -5, we get {0,7,2}, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the generator 5 and 7 sets are inversionally related, sets of the same cardinality are equivalent, so the set with cardinality 5 is the pentatonic scale, cardinality 6 is the hexatonic scale, cardinality 7 is the diatonic collection, cardinality 8 is the bebop scale, and cardinality 12 is the chromatic scale, or aggregate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s now look at the generator of 8 semitones, which gives us the set {0,8,4}. We can see that this is the inversion of the generator of 4 semitones. We can make a generalization that two generators which sum to twelve will generate equivalent, but inversionally-related collections, i.e.: generators 1 and 11, generators 2 and 10, 3 and 9, 4 and 8, 5 and 7. Generator 6 sums to 12 with itself, so it has no inversion partner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What other generalizations can we make? Well, perhaps the most important one is that only generators which are coprime with 12 will generate the entire chromatic scale or aggregate. There are only four such generators: 1 and its inversion partner 11, 5 and its inversion partner 7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s extend that a bit further by looking at the Greatest Common Divisor of each generator and 12. For any generator a, a collection of 12/gcd(a,12) members will be created, and the number of unique collections within the aggregate will be gcd(a,12).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generator 1: gcd(1,12)=1 unique collection of 12/1=12 members&lt;br&gt;
Generator 2: gcd(2,12)=2 unique collection of 12/2=6 members&lt;br&gt;
Generator 3: gcd(3,12)=3 unique collection of 12/3=4 members&lt;br&gt;
Generator 4: gcd(4,12)=4 unique collection of 12/3=3 members&lt;br&gt;
Generator 5: gcd(5,12)=1 unique collection of 12/1=12 members&lt;br&gt;
Generator 6: gcd(6,12)=6 unique collection of 12/6=2 members&lt;br&gt;
Generator 7: gcd(7,12)=1 unique collection of 12/1=12 members&lt;br&gt;
Generator 8: gcd(8,12)=4 unique collection of 12/4=3 members&lt;br&gt;
Generator 9: gcd(9,12)=3 unique collection of 12/3=4 members&lt;br&gt;
Generator 10: gcd(10,12)=2 unique collection of 12/2=6 members&lt;br&gt;
Generator 11: gcd(11,12)=1 unique collection of 12/1=12 members&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The symmetry of these collections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to looking at the pitch class sets that result from these generators, it is also helpful to think of them as interval sets. For example, let&#39;s look at generator 5, cardinality 5 though 8:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cardinality 5, pentatonic: {5-5-5-5-5}&lt;br&gt;
Cardinality 6, hexatonic: {5-5-5-5-5-5}&lt;br&gt;
Cardinality 7, diatonic: {5-5-5-5-5-5-5}&lt;br&gt;
Cardinality 8, bebop: {5-5-5-5-5-5-5-5}&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that becomes instantly clear is that each of these sets is symmetrical. The pentatonic collection has an axis of symmetry on its 3rd member, the hexatonic collection has an axis of symmetry between its 3rd and 4th members, the diatonic collection has an axis of symmetry on its 4th member (which corresponds to the dorian mode in scale form), and the bebop scale has an axis of symmetry between its 4th and 5th members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Subset relations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other aspects which become instantly obvious when looking at these generated collections through their interval sets are their mutual subset and superset relations. Let&#39;s look at the interval sets again, this time without labels:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{5-5-5-5-5}&lt;br&gt;
{5-5-5-5-5-5}&lt;br&gt;
{5-5-5-5-5-5-5}&lt;br&gt;
{5-5-5-5-5-5-5-5}&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can now see very clearly that the pentatonic is a subset of the hexatonic, which is a subset of the diatonic, which is a subset of the bebop scale. It also makes is easy to see that the hexatonic contains two pentatonic sets. To see this, align the first member of the pentatonic with the first member of the hexatonic; that is the first subset. Now align the first member of the pentatonic with the second member of the hexatonic; that is the second subset. Likewise, the diatonic contains three pentatonic sets, and the bebop scale contains four pentatonic sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Key takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following sets commonly used in jazz are each generated by repeating a single interval: the chromatic scale, the wholetone scale, the diminished 7th chord, the augmented triad, the pentatonic scale, the hexatonic scale, the diatonic collection, including all modes, the bebop scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of the above listed sets is symmetrical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pentatonic is a subset of the hexatonic, which is a subset of the diatonic, which is a subset of the bebop scale.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Understanding Key Signatures</title>
    <link href="https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/understanding-key-signatures/" />
    <updated>2024-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/understanding-key-signatures/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I suspect that when most people first learn about key signatures, they learn them by rote memorization. When first learning to read music on an instrument, a student will commonly begin with pieces in C major, with no sharps or flats in the key signature. Next, the student might begin playing pieces in G major, or F major, with one sharp and one flat, respectively. Gradually, the student will play pieces with more and more sharps or flats, memorizing which key signatures go with which keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, the student will be introduced to a system usually called “the order of sharps and flats,” or something similar. Probably at this time, the student will also be shown the famous “circle of fifths” diagram. When I was first taught the order of sharps and flats, it was taught to me as something that just needed to be memorized, along with a handy mnemonic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Order of sharps: F-C-G-D-A-E-B. “Father Charles Goes Down And Ends Battle.”&lt;br&gt;
Order of flats: B-E-A-D-G-C-F. “Battle Ends And Down Goes Charles’ Father.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One very good thing about that particular mnemonic is that it can be read, and makes sense forward and backward. That illustrates a very important aspect of the order of sharps and flats: each is the retrograde of the other. On the other hand, there is one very bad thing about the mnemonic: it is not necessary, and it obscures the structure behind the two orders. Instead of a mnemonic, I will offer the following definition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definition: The order of sharps is a series of six perfect fifths, starting on F; the order of flats is a series of six perfect fourths, starting on B.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would assert that a student should learn intervals well enough to be able to spell a series of prefect fifths or perfect fourths without the need of a mnemonic, much the same as a student should be able to spell any triad or seventh chord. If, instead of simply memorizing a mnemonic, we take a close look at the structure of the order of sharps and the order of flats, we can make some observations that lead to a deeper understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observation 1: The order of sharps and the order of flats each include all seven notes of the diatonic collection&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/understanding-key-signatures/#fn1&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, in C.&lt;/strong&gt; While this may seem obvious, or a trivial observation, the surprising fact is that you can spell a diatonic collection simply by adding six successive perfect fifths, or perfect fourths, from any starting note. The term for this is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/generated-collections&quot;&gt;generated collection&lt;/a&gt;, where a single repeated interval acts as a generator to create a collection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observation 2: The order of sharps and flats are both symmetrical, therefore the diatonic collection is symmetrical.&lt;/strong&gt; Since the same interval separates each two successive pitches, the intervallic structure is the same in both directions. It is also apparent that for the diatonic collection in C, the axis of symmetry is on the note D, which appears in the center of both the order of sharps and the order of flats. As a corollary to this, one can see that the Dorian mode is in fact symmetrical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observation 3: The order of sharps and flats are both bounded by a tritone. By definition, each diatonic collection contains only one tritone.&lt;/strong&gt; The order of sharps begins on the 4th scale degree and ends on the leading tone. The order of flats begins on the leading tone and ends on the 4th scale degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have some insight into the structure of the order of sharps and flats, we can explore exactly why the sharps and flats come in exactly the order that they do. In order to do that, let’s create a new definition for the diatonic collection:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definition: A diatonic collection consists of exactly six perfect fifths, or exactly six perfect fourths, and exactly one tritone.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With our definition in place, we can begin experimenting with accidentals needed to transform one diatonic collection into another. Let’s start with the diatonic collection in C:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F-C-G-D-A-E-B&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say that we want to add a single accidental, a sharp, to transform this into a different diatonic collection. We try C#, but now we have two tritones, thus failing our definition. Try G#, same result. Try D#, same result, and so forth. There is, in fact, only one note we can make sharp and still match our definition: F#. Now we have the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F#-C-G-D-A-E-B&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That meets our definition perfectly, but the order of intervals is different, so let’s move the F# to the end of the chain. Now, once again, we have our tritone at the boundaries:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C-G-D-A-E-B-F#&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we again try adding a single sharp to the various notes, we again find that only one note can be made sharp, and still match our definition: C#. Once again, we move the C# to the end of the chain to keep the tritone at the boundaries. Now we have the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;G-D-A-E-B-F#-C#&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we keep experimenting, it becomes clear that in order to match our definition, the only note we can alter is one of the boundary notes. Recall that the boundary notes are always a tritone. So the only procedure that works is to “fix” the tritone at the boundary into a perfect fifth, shift that note to the end of the chain, and thereby create a new tritone at the boundary. Continuing this process, these are the results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D-A-E-B-F#-C#-G#&lt;br&gt;
A-E-B-F#-C#-G#-D#&lt;br&gt;
E-B-F#-C#-G#-D#-A#&lt;br&gt;
B-F#-C#-G#-D#-A#-E#&lt;br&gt;
F#-C#-G#-D#-A#-E#-B#&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we can see, there is nothing arbitrary about this order. It is, in fact, the only order in which we can add one sharp at a time and create a new correct diatonic collection with each step. If instead, we transform each collection by adding a single flat each time, to process is similar. Each time, we add a flat to “fix” the boundary tritone into a perfect fourth, thus creating a single new boundary tritone:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B-E-A-D-G-C-F&lt;br&gt;
E-A-D-G-C-F-Bb&lt;br&gt;
A-D-G-C-F-Bb-Eb&lt;br&gt;
D-G-C-F-Bb-Eb-Ab&lt;br&gt;
G-C-F-Bb-Eb-Ab-Db&lt;br&gt;
C-F-Bb-Eb-Ab-Db-Gb&lt;br&gt;
F-Bb-Eb-Ab-Db-Gb-Cb&lt;br&gt;
Bb-Eb-Ab-Db-Gb-Cb-Fb&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, this order of adding a single flat at a time to create a new diatonic collection is the only one that works. It is also important to reiterate that in each step, we are “fixing” the previous tritone and creating a new tritone at the boundary. Therefore, the last accidental in each order represents a member of the single tritone that belongs to that collection. In Observation 3 above, we noted that the order of sharps always ends on the leading tone, and the order of flats always ends on the 4th scale degree. Now we have an understanding of exactly why this is the case. We can also utilize the common advice to “go up a semitone from the last sharp, go down a perfect fourth from the last flat,” to find the name of the major key from its signature—but, once again, now we understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;footnotes-sep&quot;&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-item&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m using the term &amp;quot;collection&amp;quot; here rather than &amp;quot;scale&amp;quot; because we are thinking about all the possible relations between pitches, and not any one particular ordering. &lt;a href=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/understanding-key-signatures/#fnref1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dominant 7b5 and the Diminished, Altered, and Wholetone Scales</title>
    <link href="https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/" />
    <updated>2023-02-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A version of this post first appeared on my blog at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chesterjankowski.com/resources-for-jazz-guitar-three-octave-runs/&quot;&gt;www.chesterjankowski.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Three-octave scales and commonalities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the exercises that I do on a daily basis have been suggested to me by one of my many teachers over the years, but here is one that I came up with on my own four or five years ago. I think it might be a good one for intermediate jazz guitarists who feel uncomfortable with the following scales: diminished, altered, lydian dominant, whole-tone. In the course of the lesson, we will come up with a good fingering for a three-octave run of all the scales mentioned, and also gain some insight on how the scales are connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key to the lesson is the arpeggio in example 1. You can think of it as a Dominant 7 b5 arpeggio (b5 or #4, but let’s not get wrapped around the axle on that, please). Before we go any further, please pick up your guitar and play through the arpeggio. In itself, it is a nice warmup, with a gentle stretch between the 1st and 4th fingers. As you play the arpeggio, think about the intervals it outlines; a major third, up a major second and cross strings, then repeat. Or alternatively, a major third, then up a tritone from where you started, then repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/WHuSx--lqU-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/WHuSx--lqU-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Dom7b5 arpeggio, 3 octaves to the 7th&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;999&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;Ex. 1&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you continue to play the arpeggio, you will notice that the major third on each string creates a gap of three semitones between the 1st and 4th fingers. “How can we fill in that gap? Ah!” Let’s start by filling in the gap with the note in the middle. That note is one whole tone above the 1st finger and one whole tone under the 4th finger. Playing it through, it looks like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/OUCnlta7aw-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/OUCnlta7aw-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wholetone 3 octaves to the 7th&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;1283&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Ex. 2&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, so now we have a nice fingering for a three octave whole tone scale. With this fingering, it is easy to see the symmetry of the scale–the fingering does not contradict the symmetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By adding one note in the middle of the gap, we maintain the symmetry. What if we want to add two notes into the gap? If we add a semitone above the 1st finger, and another semitone below the 4th finger, we end up with the three octave diminished scale in example 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/8KMZQTGZCG-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/8KMZQTGZCG-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Diminished 3 octaves to 7th&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;1241&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Ex. 3&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very important fingering for the diminished scale. Once again, the fingering illuminates the scale’s underlying symmetry, it does not contradict it. And because of the repeated fingering pattern, it should be possible to get this run very fast with some practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, now we have seen two ways to fill in the gap in our original arpeggio, with one note in the middle, and with two notes a semitone above and below the 1st and 4th fingers. What else can we try? Well, as the meme goes, “why not both?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our next run, we will follow the pattern ‘add two notes’, then ‘add one note’, and repeat that up the strings. What we end up with is the altered scale in example 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/nj6VOzho5j-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img 3=&quot;&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/nj6VOzho5j-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;![&quot; Altered=&quot;&quot; octaves=&quot;&quot; to=&quot;&quot; 7th&quot;=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;1266&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Ex. 4&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The altered scale is sometimes called the “diminished, whole tone” scale, and this fingering makes that label very clear. It is literally four notes of diminished followed by three notes of whole tone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, so we tried ‘add two notes’, followed by ‘add one note’. What if we reverse the order, and try ‘add one note’ followed by ‘add two notes’? Now we end up with example 5, which is the lydian dominant scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/9RddPGCwTg-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/9RddPGCwTg-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Lydian dominant 3 octaves to the 7th&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;1333&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Ex. 5&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I love about these fingerings for altered and lydian dominant, is, once again, they make plain the relationship of the two scales, most importantly, how they pair with each other at the tritone. G altered is C# lydian dominant; G lydian dominant is C# altered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have already covered a lot of material. So maybe now is a good time to pause and just think about the one arpeggio and three scales we just covered. As a matter of fact, you could just stop now and get about 80% of this lesson. If you practice the above material every day for a month, you’ll find that you have a new facility with these scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where to next? Well, while it’s good to practice mixing 8ths, 16ths and triplets, it’s also a good idea to practice these scales with a constant rhythm. Triplets are always good with three octave scales. Examples 6 and 7 take our altered and lydian dominant scales into a constant triplet rhythm. Note that, while our fingering patterns were perfectly aligned with the meter in the previous examples, and now they’re not. That’s fine. You should obviously also practice these fingerings with other rhythmic patterns too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/zdnhZAQUhF-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/zdnhZAQUhF-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Altered 3 octaves to 7th&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;1350&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Ex. 6&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/bCS4izMMvi-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/bCS4izMMvi-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Lydian dominant 3 octaves to 7th&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;1366&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Ex. 7&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the previous examples have been three octaves up to the 7th only. That has been on purpose, so that the fingerings are symmetrical up and down (at least in examples 1 – 5). But it’s also desirable to practice these scales and arpeggios all the way up to the tonic. Example 8 shows our original arpeggio, all the way up to the high G.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/5ec5AT84cp-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/5ec5AT84cp-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Dominant 7th arpeggio 3 octaves to tonic&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;1033&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Ex. 8&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples 9, 10, and 11 take our diminished, altered, and lydian dominant scales up a full three octaves to the tonic. You should practice these, along with the full three octave whole tone scale, which should be easy to figure out at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/pA5BDjPnyq-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/pA5BDjPnyq-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Diminished 3 octaves to tonic&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;1383&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Ex. 9&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/AIP4gCLiwh-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/AIP4gCLiwh-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Altered 3 octaves to tonic&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;1333&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Ex. 10&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/1t6lYXbEp8-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/1t6lYXbEp8-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Lydian dominant 3 octaves to tonic&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;1591&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Ex. 11&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that if you have followed along this far, you have gained some insight into how the dominant 7 b5 arpeggio is the common link between the whole tone, diminished, altered, and lydian dominant scales. I hope you find the fingerings useful. This concludes the ‘conventional’ part of this lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Further afield&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we want to continue exploring the above ideas? Well, since we have looked at elements of two-, three-, and four-note groupings, what if we began to combine them in other ways as well?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In example 4, the altered scale up and down forms a perfect palindrome, in pitch as well as in rhythm. One interesting way to break the palindrome in shown in example 12. Now our groupings are 4-3-4-3-4-3… This creates an ascending altered scale followed by a descending lydian dominant scale. It’s an interesting color.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/ziC1T6Kayi-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/ziC1T6Kayi-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Altered up, lydian dominant down&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;1383&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Ex. 12&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example 13 does a similar treatment with groupings of 3-4-3-4… This creates an ascending lydian dominant followed by a descending altered scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/WYHs_SIxki-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/WYHs_SIxki-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Lydian dominant up, altered down&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;1450&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Ex. 13&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally in example 14, we are mixing and matching all the elements: fragments of the arpeggio, and all four scales. Once all the elements in this lesson are fluent, you can combine them in endless way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/5xMipOOuSX-5100.webp 5100w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://resourcesforjazzguitar.com/diminished-altered-wholetone/5xMipOOuSX-5100.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Hybrid&quot; width=&quot;5100&quot; height=&quot;1433&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Ex. 14&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s all for this lesson, and there is enough material here to keep one busy for quite a while. I would love to hear any feedback or questions. I would also be happy to make a PDF of the exercises available to anyone who asks.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>